Good morning. Today's דף daf *Daf* is ק״ט *Kof Tet*. We are
behind, so we pick up at the very top of ק״ח *Kof
Chet* עמוד ב׳ *Amud Bet*, where we're explicating various פסוקים psukim *Pesukim*
from the הלל Hallel. *Hallel*.
So let's take a look. We pick up on רבי Rebbi נתן
אומר *Rabbi Natan Omer*, seven lines from the top. ואמת ה׳ לעולם
הללויה *Ve'emet Hashem Le'olam Haleluyah*, right? So we said before that who
said that? So we said גבריאל Gavriel *Gabriel* said it when he
was given the right to save חנניה מישאל ועזריה *Chananyah Mishael Ve'azaryah*.
So now it says דגים שבים אמרוה *Dagim Shebayam Amruha*, the fish
in the sea said it. Now we're going to tie it back
to the story of יציאה yetziah. ממצרים *Yetziat Mitzrayim*. דגים שבים אמרוה
*Dagim Shebayam Amruha*, like רב הונא דאמר D'amar
רב הונא *Rav Huna De'amar Rav Huna*, ישראל Yisrael. שבאותו הדור מקטני
אמנה היו *Yisrael Shebe'oto Hador Mikatney Amanah Hayu*,
the Jewish people, ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael*, at that generation were of those
weak of faith, small of faith. וכהדרש רבה בר מארי *Vechehadrash Rabba
Bar Mari*, like רבה בר מארי *Rabba Bar Mari* explicated: מאי דכתיב
Mai dikhtiv, *Mai Dechtiv*, what's meant by the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* in
תהילים *Tehillim*, וימרו על ים בים סוף *Vayamru Al Yam Beyam Suf*,
that they rebelled on the sea by the ים סוף Yam Suf,
*Yam Suf*, by the Sea of Reeds? מלמד שהמרו ישראל Yisrael, באותה
שעה *Melamed Shehimru Yisrael Be'otah Sha'ah*, that even at the moment of
the splitting of the sea, the בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael *Bnei Yisrael*
rebelled and they said, כשם שאנו עולים מצד אחד כך מצריים עולים
מצד אחר *Keshem She'anu Olim Mitzad Echad Kach Mitzrayim Olim Mitzad Acher*,
hey God, just the same way, you know, they said to משה
Moshe *Moshe*, very nice you saved us, but the same way we're
coming up on this side, you know, maybe the Egyptians have found
another path through the sea and they're coming up on somewhere else.
אמר Amar, לו הקדוש ברוך הוא *Amar Lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu*, God
said לשר של ים *Lesar Shel Yam*, the angel over the ocean
or over the Red Sea, פלוט אותם ליבשה *Pelot Otam Leyabashah*, spit
out the Egyptians onto the dry land so they'll see that they
had been drowned. אמר amar לפניו lefanav *Amar Lefanav*, so this angel
said, רבונו של עולם Ribbono Shel Olam, *Ribbono Shel Olam*, כלום יש
עבד שנותן לרבו מתנה וחוזר ונוטל הימנה *Klum Yesh Eved Shenoten Lerabo
Matanah Vechozer Venotel Heimenah*? Is there ever a slave that the master
will give him a gift and then demand that the gift be
back? You've given me all these Egyptians, they're food for all the
fishes in the sea. So you want me to give it back?
אמר לו *Amar Lo*, so he said, אפרע לך אחד ומחצה שבהן
*Efra Lecha Echad Umchetza Shebahen*, I'll give you back one and a
half times this in the future. אמר לו *Amar Lo*, so he
said back, רבונו של עולם Ribbono Shel Olam, *Ribbono Shel Olam*, יש
עבד שתובע את רבו *Yesh Eved Shetoveh Et Rabo*? How could I
ever ask it from you? Would it ever be appropriate for a
slave to say, hey master, you owe me this? I don't have
an ability to request it of you. We'll see. אמר לו *Amar
Lo*, נחל קישון Nachal Kishon. יהיה לי ערב *Nachal Kishon Yihiyeh Li
Arev*. No, you know what? Fine. You won't have to ask it
for me. The וואדי *Wadi*, the river of נחל קישון Nachal Kishon
*Nachal Kishon*, that'll be my guarantor, so you can ask it from
the נחל קישון Nachal Kishon, *Nachal Kishon*, you don't have to ask
it from me and you'll be entitled to demand it back.
Who's the לו *Lo*? The head of the angel over the ocean
that's being asked to tell the ocean to spit out the Egyptians.
Okay. מיד miyad פלט אותם ליבשה *Miyad Pelat Otam Leyabashah*.
So the angel over the ocean spit out the Egyptians onto the
dry land so בני ישראל Yisrael, *Bnei Yisrael* could see that the
Egyptians had died. ובאו ישראל וראו אותם *Uba'u Yisrael Vera'u Otam*, and
the בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael* came and they saw them, שנאמר וירא
ישראל את מצרים מת על שפת הים *Shene'emar Vayar Yisrael Et Mitzrayim
Met Al Sfat Hayam*. So they saw them on the actually, you
know, by the seashore, by the edge of
the ocean, they had seen that they had been spit out by
the seashore. מאי
אחד ומחצה שבהן *Mai Echad Umchetza Shebahen*? So what's this one and
a half times? Or what's really the end of this story? דאילו
בפרעה כתיב *De'ilu Bepharaoh Ketiv*, by פרעה *Pharaoh* it says, שש מאות
רכב בחור *Shesh Me'ot Rechev Bachur*, six hundred chosen chariotmen. ואילו בסיסרא
כתיב *Ve'ilu BeSisra Ketiv*, and this is now the end of the
story, by סיסרא *Sisra*, right, who came to war and it was
דבורה וברק *Devorah Vebarak* and so on, it says, תשע מאות רכב
ברזל *Tesha Me'ot Rechev Barzel*, nine hundred, that's one and a half
times, nine hundred iron chariots. כי אתא סיסרא *Ki Ata Sisra*, when
סיסרא *Sisra* came, אתא לייהו בדקרי דפרזלא *Ata Leyhu Bedikrey Deparzala*. So
they approached to attack the ישראל *Yisrael* with these spears of iron.
הוציא הקדוש ברוך הוא עליהם כוכבים ממסילותם *Hotzi Hakadosh Baruch Hu Aleihem
Kochavim Mimesilotam*.
God caused the stars to come out from their normal orbits, thank
you, and to come closer to the earth to burn them up,
to burn them. דכתיב d'chsiv, *Dechtiv*, now obviously this is based on
the שירת דבורה *Shirat Devorah*, מן השמים נלחמו הכוכבים *Min Hashamayim Nilchamu
Hakochavim*, the stars fought against them from the heavens. כיון דנחיתו כוכבי
שמיא עלייהו *Keivan Denachitu Kochvey Shamaya Aleiheu*, once the stars lowered down
a little bit, came out against them, אקדירו הני דקרי דפרזלא *Akdiru
Hani Dikrey Deparzala*, those iron spears got hot. נחיתו לאקרורי נפשייהו בנחל
קישון *Nachitu Le'akruri Nafsheihu Benachal Kishon*. They went to cool themselves off.
ומה שחין נפשייהו בנחל קישון *Uma Shachin Nafsheihu Benachal Kishon*? So they
went to bathe in נחל Nachal, קישון *Nachal Kishon*. So? What about
the spears?
No, נפשייהו *Nafsheihu*, the people, they're holding the spears, their hands are
burning, so they ran to get some water. So they ran to
נחל קישון *Nachal Kishon*.
And someone pointed it out right before the story mentioned that the
בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael* did not have any iron, any armor. Oh,
that's a good point, okay, so they couldn't fight back, otherwise בני
ישראל *Bnei Yisrael* would have had...
Thank you very much, that's a good point that I had passed
over. Anyway, so right, if there's no iron for בני ישראל, that's
why it only affects Sisra's armies. Thank you for that. So they
went to cool themselves, what? Oh, they went to cool themselves off.
אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא לנחל קישון, Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'Nachal Kishon,
so there they are they're all bathing in נחל קישון. אמר,
perfect opportunity! אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא לנחל קישון לך והשב ערבונך. Amar
Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'Nachal Kishon: Lech vehashev ervoncha. Go and pay back
your surety, you are the guarantor. מיד גרפם נחל קישון, Miyad garafam
Nachal Kishon, נחל קישון swept them up והשפיכם לים, v'hishpicham layam, cast
them into the sea, שנאמר נחל קישון גרפם נחל קדומים. shene'emar Nachal
Kishon garafam Nachal Kedumim.
נחל קישון, so it swept them away, the נחל, the wadi of
ancient times or of the past. מאי נחל קדומים נחל שנעשה ערב
מקדם. Mai Nachal Kedumim? Nachal shenasa arev mi'kedem. It had long ago
been made the guarantor. באותה שעה פתחו דגים של ים, V'otah sha'ah
patchu digim shel yam, at that moment the fish of the sea
opened up ואמרו ואמת ה' לעולם. v'amru Ve'emes Hashem l'olam. Even the
fish said: God ultimately is true, God keeps his promises. So he
doesn't only keep his promises to angels and to us, he even
keeps his promises to the fish. I guess it was a promise
really to the angel, but the fish got paid back.
Let's just finish the סוגיא, sugya, then I'll ask you a question.
Okay. אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש מאי דכתיב? Amar Rabi Shimon ben
Lakish: Mai d'ksiv? What's meant by the verse מושיבי עקרת הבית אם
הבנים שמחה הללויה? Moshivi akeres habayis em habanim smeicha halelukah? So this
is again finishing the darshaning on פסוקים psukim of the הלל. Hallel.
אמרה כנסת ישראל לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amra kneses Yisrael lifnei Hakadosh
Baruch Hu, so the people of Israel said to God: ריבונו של
עולם, Ribbono Shel Olam, שמוני בניך כחולדה זו הדירה בעיקרי הבתים. smuni
banayich kachulda zu hadara b'ikrei habatim. Your children have made me like
this weasel that dwells in the like cracks, crevices of the house.
So עקרת הבית akeres habayis is the crevices of the house. Now
what does it mean they've made me like this weasel? So the
רשב"ם Rashbam says it means that
it means that they have through their sins I've had to be,
you know, they've made me lowly like this weasel, עקרת הבית. akeres
habayis. And now it's אם הבנים שמחה, em habanim smeicha, but now
I am rejoicing because now you know at the time of redemption
things have reversed themselves. Again, I don't understand why that is a
more powerful metaphor than just the idea of a barren woman, to
think about this weasel in the cracks of the house. But anyway,
yes,
Rivka.
The about the angel helping
helping him out, it's the שביעי של פסח Shevii shel Pesach that
we
say אני ולא מלאך, ani velo malach, אני ולא אחר ani velo
acher that we say,
that's talking about
קריעת ים סוף? Kriyas Yam Suf? Well, look, that's in general an
issue because we also say right, I mean the אני ולא מלאך
ani velo malach is even more by the actual מכת בכורות makkas
bechoros and the יציאה. And there what it says, you know, but
there also but I'm saying but there we also have this idea
of ולא יתן המשחית לבוא אל בתיכם לנגוף. velo yiten hamashchis lavo
el bateichem lingof. So that whole sense of, you know, God alone
as opposed to, but yes, but here anyway, it wasn't even in
the act of the קריעת ים סוף Kriyas Yam Suf for the
drowning of the ים סוף, it was only in this very secondary
thing of like, you know, of having the Egyptians go out to
the edge of the sea. So but I do think that there
is some of that issue there, you're right. The מדרש Midrash very
emphasizes אני הוא ולא אחר, ani hu velo acher, and then in
the מדרשים Midrashim and even to some degree in the פסוקים pesukim
by the משחית mashchis you don't have, you know, you have some
counter-voices there. I think that that's correct. I don't know other than
this being a great story for kids, I don't know what deeper
meaning to read into this whole thing.
There is an ancient idea about fish. Uh-huh. In other words, ancient
religions that think about fish, fish are eternal, fish don't die, fish
are sacred. Interesting. It's a motif. Okay. It's unusual isn't it that
כנסת ישראל Kneses Yisrael is a separate entity from the people?
Well, that's a good point too, you're right because the רשב"ם Rashbam
says שמוני בניך, smuni banayich, so the רשב"ם Rashbam says כנסת ישראל
Kneses Yisrael means הזקנים והחשובים שבהם. hazekeinim vehachashuvim shebahem. You know, but
that's a good point. I mean, in what do you call it,
in Kabbalistic thought, כנסת ישראל Kneses Yisrael is basically שכינה Shechinah and
it represents it, it refers to sort of, you know, so it's
actually sort of the the almost divine, I can't even explain. But
anyway, it's not just the physical Jewish people, it's some type of
the of a metaphysical entity that actually almost
is an emanation of the divine that represents the Jewish people. So
but anyway, I've said too much, I can't, I see she was
also talking with God, yes.
Right, I mean that's the whole thing, the yes, I
mean these מדרשים, Midrashim, right, these מדרשים Midrashim with everybody having these
debates before God and having to barter and God promising and this
and that, I mean they're very, you know, sort of graphic, they
seize the imagination, but I'm not sure how to how to explain
it in meaningful, yeah, God, yeah. Sure. Right, I mean look, it's
completely true. In the תורה, Torah, look, in the תורה, Torah, that's
completely correct. In the תורה, Torah, even in thinking about the angels
in the תורה, Torah, like we're just about to come up to
a whole story right with angels, right? The whole story that we
read about them visiting אברהם Avraham and then with the עקידה, Akeida,
you know, there's a complete distance between the angels and God and
they're just like these earthly whatever they are that are doing you
know... so God sitting in and so on, even in the visions
in יחזקאל, Yechezkel, you know, they're some type of divine retinue. It's
really, maybe I'm forgetting it, but I think the only place I
know in תנ״ך Tanakh where you have some sense of like a
of a of almost like a discussion, you know, and angel as
a personality in God's presence is in איוב, Iyov, the beginning of
איוב Iyov where the שטן Satan comes and says, "Hey, what about
איוב?" Iyov? and blah blah blah. And then rabbinic literature you got,
you know, it's it it blows up this whole thing. "Oh, what
about this? He's gonna pay me back, blah blah blah." And you
know, again, I don't really know what to make of it, I
mean it's but I agree, it certainly, you know, not it's not
a comfortable theology, you know, I think for most of us. Okay,
but let's let's continue
now.
So, גמרא Gemara says like this: דרש רבא, Darash Rava, so רבא
Rava explicated. מאי דכתיב, mai dikhtiv, so again we're looking at פסוקים
pesukim, in the הלל. Hallel. What's meant by the פסוק pasuk אהבתי
כי ישמע ה׳, Ahavti ki yishma Hashem, "I have loved that God
has heard the voice of my
supplication"? אמר כנסת ישראל לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar Knesset Yisrael lifnei
Hakadosh Baruch Hu, the people of Israel said, the congregation of Israel
said: רבונו של עולם, אימתי אני אהובה לפניך? ematai ani ahuva lefanecha?
When am I beloved to You? בשעה שתשמע קול תחנוני, bishaa shetishma
kol tachanunai, when You hear my supplication. So rather than reading אהבתי,
Ahavti, "I have loved," it's reading "I have been loved," when God
has heard the voice of my supplication. So it's sort of, you
know, it's sort of saying our relationship, God, is, you know, or
demonstrate Your love for me by hearing my
supplication and that is what, you know, it shows that I am
beloved to You but it also it also creates that reality of
being beloved to You. דלותי ולי יהושיע, Dalosi veli yehoshia, "I have
been low and God has saved me." אמר כנסת ישראל לפני הקדוש
ברוך הוא: Amar Knesset Yisrael lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu: רבונו של עולם,
אף על פי שדלה אני במצוות, af al pi shedala ani bemitzvot,
although I might be poor in מצוות, mitzvot, לך אני, lecha ani,
I belong to You, ולי ולי, veli veli, meaning you know to
me, meaning as this is our relationship, ולי נאה להושיע, veli na'eh
lehoshia, it is fit to to save me. So again this sort
of sense of God, you know, calling upon the relationship, right? You
I am beloved that You when You hear my voice. Yes, I
am poor, but we are but I am true to You or
you know we this is our unique relationship, please save me. So
I'm not saying because of my מצוות, mitzvot, I'm not saying I
deserve it, but do this because of Your love to me, do
this because of our relationship, because I have, you know, because because
I am true to You.
אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, so said רב כהנא, Rav Kahana,
כשחלה רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, kshachala Rabbi Yishmael beRabbi Yosi, when רבי
ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael beRabbi Yosi got sick, שלח לו רבי,
shalakh lo Rebbi, רבי Rebbi sent him: אמור לנו שנים או שלשה
דברים שאמרת לנו משום אביך, emor lanu shenayim o shelosha devarim she'amarta
lanu mishum avicha,
tell us two or three things you've said in the name of
your father, like maybe he was afraid he was going to die
and he didn't want these teachings to be lost. Now the רשב״ם
Rashbam interestingly says, I'll just break for a minute if you look
here in the רשב״ם, Rashbam, about fifteen lines before the lines get
wide, כשחלה רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, kshachala Rabbi Yishmael beRabbi Yosi, he
says very interestingly point, בהרבה מקומות בש״ס מצינו ששלח לו רבי לרבי
ישמעאל ברבי יוסי
בחליו, beharbeh mekomot baShas matzinu sheshalakh lo Rebbi leRabbi Yishmael beRabbi Yosi
bechelyo, in a number of places in ש״ס Shas we find that
רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael beRabbi Yosi got sick and רבי
Rebbe, sent him and said tell us some things that your father
said. והדברים שהשיב לו כאן לא השיב לו פעם אחרת, vehadevarim sheheshiv
lo kan lo heshiv lo pa'am acheret, and if you look in
one of the stories, the answers he gave wasn't same as the
things he said in another story. So he says two possible explanations:
ושמא חלה הרבה רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי, vashema chala harbeh Rabbi Yishmael
beRabbi Yosi,
maybe he got sick a lot and ובכל פעם פעם שלח לו
רבי והוא משיב לו, bechol pa'am pa'am shalakh lo Rebbi vehu meshiv
lo, and every time he got more information and a different answer.
אינמי כולן השיבם בפעם אחת, inami kulan heshivim befa'am echat,
he actually gave all of these answers, ובש״ס סידרם במסכתות כל אחת
במקומה, uvaShas sidreim masekhtot kol achat bimkomah,
but the גמרא Gemara broke them up into different locations.
So it's because of two or three and then he said...
All right, what can I tell you? He said two or three,
he gave him twenty, so it had to divide into ten stories.
Anyway, back to the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay. So two or three things that you said in the name
of your father. שלח לו, shalakh lo, he said: כך
אמר אבא, kach amar abba, this is what my father said. מאי
דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, what's meant by the פסוק pasuk, הללו את ה׳
כל גוים שבחוהו כל האומים, Halelu et Hashem kol goyim shabechuhu kol
ha'ummim, אומות העולם מאי עבידתייהו, umot ha'olam mai avidtaihu, what
what why the nations praising God? Especially in the end of the
פסוק, pasuk. כי גבר עלינו חסדו. ki gavar aleinu chasdo.
So what's הללו את ה׳ כל גוים? Halelu et Hashem kol goyim?
הכי קאמר: hakhi ka'amar: הללו את ה׳ כל גוים Halelu et Hashem
kol goyim אגבורות ונפלאות
דעביד בהדייהו, agvurot venifla'ot de'avid behadaihu, you the nations praise God for
the wonders God has done with you, just the wonders of creation
and of nature and of all the wonders God does for the
world. כל שכן אנו kol sheken anu כי גבר עלינו חסדו, ki
degevar aleinu chasdo,
how much more so כי גבר עלינו חסדו, ki gavar aleinu chasdo,
the special relationship we have with God demands for us even more
that we praise God. Okay ועוד ve'od or שלח לו ועוד, shalakh
lo ve'od, עתידה מצרים שתביא דורון למשיח, atida Mitzrayim shetavi doron leMashiach,
at the end of days when משיח Mashiach comes the Egyptians or
you know
the entity of Egypt whatever it is will bring will bring gifts
to the משיח. Mashiach. קסבר אינו מקבל מהם, kasavar eino mekabel mehem,
so משיח Mashiach will figure I'm not going to accept that from
them. אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשיח, amar lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu
leMashiach, God says to the משיח: Mashiach: קבל מהם, kabel mehem, accept
it from them. אכסניא עשו לבני במצרים, achsanya asu levanai beMitzrayim,
they were a host to my children in Egypt, even though they
put them into slavery, they still also were willing to you know
have them in the land. מיד Miyad, oh so get you're accepting
from the Egyptians, ויאתיו... vayetayu... ויאתיו חשמנים מני מצרים *vaye'etayu chashmanim mini
Mitzrayim*, the noble people from Egypt came. So נשא כוש קל וחומר
לעצמה *nasa Kush kal vachomer le'atzma*. So Ethiopia made a קל וחומר
*kal vachomer*. ומה הללו שנשתעבדו בהן *Umah halalu she'nishta'abdu bahem*, if the
Egyptians that they enslaved the Jews, כך *kach*, that's what they'll still
be, their gifts will be accepted, אני שלא נשתעבדתי בהן *ani she'lo
nishta'abdi bahem*, לא כל kol שכן *lo kol sheken*, I who never
enslaved them, how much more so will I have my gifts be
accepted. אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא *Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu*, שגרתה לקבל מהם
*segadte lekabel mehem*, accept it from them. מיד miyad כוש תריץ ידיו
לאלהים *Miyad Kush taritz yadav l'Elohim*, כוש *Kush* will reach out his
hands to God. נשא מלכות רומי הרשעה קל וחומר בעצמה *Nasa malchus
Romi harisha kal vachomer b'atzma*. So the evil empire
of Rome made a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* itself.
What happened here? It says רומי *Romi* in there.
What? רומי *Romi*, I said רומי *Romi*. Yeah, in my גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* it was stuck back in, it was in brackets. Obviously in
some editions it was taken out. ומה הללו שאין אחיהם *Umah
halalu she'ein acheihem*, כך *kach*, their gifts are accepted, אנו שאנו אחיהם
לא כל שכן *anu she'anu acheihem lo kol sheken*, we who are
their brethren because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* associated Rome with עשו Esav
*Eisav*, how much more so will our gifts be accepted? אמר לו
הקדוש ברוך הוא לגבריאל *Amar lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu leGavriel*, so God
said to Gabriel, no longer to משיח Moshiach, *Moshiach*, we had Gabriel
at the end of the other story, גער חית קנה *ga'ar chayat
kaneh*, again from the same פסוקים pesukim, *pesukim* in תהלים *Tehillim*, this
is part of the same פרק perek *perek* of תהלים *Tehillim*, גער
חית קנה *ga'ar chayat kaneh*, yell, roar at the beast of the
reed. What does that mean? גער חיה *Ga'ar chaya*, yell at the
beast, the evil beast, Rome, reject their gift, וקנה לך עדה *u'keneh
lecha edah*, and קנה *keneh* and acquire for yourself the nation, the
congregation of Israel. So reject the Romans, your people, you know, and
in order to preserve Israel, they have been too evil to our
people to Israel. דבר אחר גער חית קנה *Davar acher ga'ar chayat
kaneh*, שדרה בין הקנים *she-dara bein hakanim*, the beast of the reed,
דכתיב יכרסמנה חזיר מיער *de-chsiv yechasmenah chazir miya'ar*, where what, what, graze,
how do you
say יכרסמנה *yechasmenah* means there?
Anyway, and
the boar of the what?
Ravages, thank you. Ravages, okay, the boar, the wild pig of the
forest will ravage, וזיז שדי ירענה *ve'ziz sadai yire'enah*, and that that
moves around in the field will graze. So anyway, so this is
the association of this פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of חזיר *chazir*, you might
remember, you know, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like why is, you
know, that that עשו Esav, *Eisav* is like the pig, because the
pig sticks out its hooves, it's the one non-kosher animal that has
split hooves, it says look how kosher I am, and really it's
טריף *treif*. So anyway this association, and of course one imagines it's
also that visceral sense that many Jews have with pigs, you know
of all the things they found that even in these ancient sites
in Israel, these archaeological sites from going back like in בית ראשון
*Bayis Rishon* period, where they'll find you know, they'll find idols and
they'll find the whole things, and the way they know whether it's
a Jewish village or a not Jewish village is that in some
of the sites there's absolutely no pork, no bones of any of
pigs. So it's actually quite fascinating, of all the things that they
can identify, you know.
We weren't idol-less but we didn't eat pork, right.
So anyway, so here's this common association of Rome and אדום *Edom*
with with the pig. So therefore anyway, so yell against that beast
of the reed. אמר רבי Rebbi חייא בר אבא אמר רבי Rebbi
יוחנן *Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan*, גער בחיה *ga'ar
be-chaya*, here's another version of it, yell against the beast, שכל מעשיה
נכתבין בקולמוס אחד *she-kol ma'aseha nichtavin bekulmos echad*. So קנה *kaneh* is
like a reed, all of its deeds are written with one reed,
meaning it always just does bad against Israel, never does any good.
So this is quite fascinating because you know, wow, yes I know.
It could also mean that God writes against them with one reed,
they only get put in the book of punishment and not of
others.
What's interesting is, you know, in other passages as well, like in
the beginning of עבודה זרה *Avodah Zarah* you have these visions of
לעתיד לבוא l'atid lavo. *le'asid lavo* and will the other nations come
forward, how much do we accept the fact that now at the
end of days when everything is good, now you want to sort
of show your fealty and be part of us and so on.
So here again it's interesting at the end of מסכת masechta, פסחים
*Masechet Pesachim* where we're also talking about the גאולה *geulah* from מצרים
*Mitzrayim*, right we're willing to have a little bit of you know,
we're willing to be
generous towards the Egyptians even though they have all of the enslavement,
but you know where the generosity ceases is in the context here
of of Rome, is it because it was seen as more harsh,
you know because there was actually the whole you know Herodian persecutions
and the and the martyrdom
and so on, I mean the Egyptians they were throwing the babies
into the sea or is it just that it was more immediate,
it was what they were living in right now so they weren't
able to have that distance and have that sense that they would
ultimately you know that they would ultimately be willing to be accept,
you know to be accepted in the future time. So I think
it's interesting and it's particularly ironic given that we've already seen that
aspects of the סדר Seder *seder* are patterned after the way in
which the wealthy people of Rome would live, so on the one
hand you have the sort of you know the mimicking
or of the of
you know of
the. oppressors' behaviors and then of course you have that deep resentment
and unwillingness to show to show any compassion.
So not compassion's the wrong word, but anyway, forgiveness. So anyway, it's
quite fascinating, I think, in the context of what we've been discussing:
Roman activity, and Egyptian, and יציאת מצרים *Yetzias Mitzrayim*, and the ליל
סדר leil seder *Leil Seder* to have this contrast here right together.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues.
Okay, where were we? עדת אבירים בעגלי עמים *Adat abbirim be-eglei amim*.
So this is a פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* from the same פרק perek
*perek* of תהילים *Tehillim*. The congregation of אבירים *abbirim* of like of
like
of strong ones, or might mean of rams, amongst the calves of
the nations. ששחטו אבירים כעגלים *She-shachtu abbirim ke-agalim*. And this is about
the martyrdom of the of you know of the הרוגי מלכות *Harugei
Malchus*, that they slaughtered the mighty ones, you know, our great sages,
like they were calves. שאין להם בעלים *She-ein lahem ba'alim*, like calves
that had no owners, like that they were ownerless, like that they
were nothing, like trash. מתרפס ברצי כסף *Mitrapes b'ratzei chesev*. So what
does that mean? שפושטים יד מתיר פת *She-poshtin yad matir pas*, which
means to open up the hand. That's how it reads, שפושטים יד
לקבל ממון *she-poshtin yad l'kabel mamon*. They want you to give them
money, taxes, or the way the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says, they accept
bribes and to tell you that they won't do their edicts. ואין
עושים רצון בעלים *V'ein osim ratzon ba'alim*, and they but they then
will go ahead, they'll take bribes and then they won't live up
to it, and they won't do what you've asked them to do.
So in terms of waiving their edicts. פיזר עמים קרבות יחפצו *Pizer
amim keravos yechpatzu*. מתרפס *Mitrapes* literally means?
I don't know.
So scattered amongst the nations or whatever, קרבות *keravos* they will desire
closeness. So מי גרם להם לישראל שיתפזרו לבין אומות העולם *Mi garam
lahem l'Yisrael she-yispazru l'vein umos ha-olam*? Now it's interesting, a little bit
of a shifting of responsibility to the Jewish people, not about Rome,
but in general about exile. Who caused the Jewish people to be
scattered throughout the nations of the world? קרבות שהיו חפצים בהם *Keravos
she-hayu chafetzim bahem*. Now what does that mean? So one explanation is
they wanted to be too close, they wanted to be too chummy.
Their desire for assimilation and their desire for like let's be like
the nations, ultimately that led to them losing their unique identity as
a people and being scattered and going into exile. Another way to
read this, though, is what the מהרש"א Maharsha *Maharsha* reads it, which
is even I think a more provocative read, which is קרבא *karva*
also means a war, right? So he says the fact that they
were too much eager for war. That in the time of the
בית ראשון *Bayis Rishon* they didn't want to just submit to the
authority of, you know, בבל *Bavel*, and in the time of the
בית שני *Bayis Sheni* they didn't want to submit to the authority
of Rome, and they too much had to go ahead and go
to war.
Is that from תנ"ך *Tanakh*? I know.
So that's part of it, but it's provocative because it's not normally
what you hear from the חז"ל *Chazal*. It's this sin or that
sin or whatever. And it's like you know what, had you just
submitted a little bit more to the authority of the non-Jews, you
would have you know you would have maintained your presence in the
Land of Israel.
Okay, so ועוד שלח לו *V'od shalach lo*. And he also sent
him about things that his father said, רבי Rebbi יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*.
תלת מאה ושישים וחמשה שווקים בכרך גדול של רומי *Tlas mei'ah v'shishim
v'chamisha shvakim b'krach gadol shel Romi*. There are 365, obviously, you know,
365 like the days of the year, 300 is usually a number
of exaggeration, but here maybe also particularly in the context of, you
know, Rome and the non-Jewish solar calendar or whatever, 365 is obviously
a number of exaggeration. Anyway, 365 marketplaces there were in the in
the metropolis of Rome. וכל אחד ואחד היו בו שלוש מאות ושישים
וחמש בירניות *V'chol echad v'echad hayu vo shalosh mei'ah v'shishim v'chamesh biraniyos*.
And each one of these of these marketplaces had
365 castles. וכל בירנית *V'chol
biranit*, and each castle, בירנית *biranit*, had שלוש מאות ושישים וחמש מעלות
*shalosh mei'ah v'shishim v'chamesh ma'alos*, had 365 stories. וכל מעלה ומעלה *V'chol
ma'alah u-ma'alah*, and each one of the stories היו בו כדי לזון
את כל העולם כולו *hayu vo k'dei lazon es kol ha-olam kulo*,
had enough grain to sustain the entire world. So Rome was hoarding
all of the grain of the world. אמר רבי שמעון ברבי לרבי
*Amar Rabbi Shimon Berabi l'Rabbi*. So Rabbi Shimon, Rabbi's son, said to
Rabbi, ואמרי לה רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yose. *v'amrei
lah Rabbi Yishmael Ber'bi Yosi*, and some say it was Rabbi Yishmael
son of Rabbi Yosi said to him, הללו למן *Halalu l'man*, who
in the end is all of this grain, all this wealth stored
up for?
He said, לך ולחברך ולחברותיך
*Lecha u'l'chavercha u'l'chavrosayich*, to you and to your
friend and to your female friends, which is really what it means,
but the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says it means your friends' friends, rather
than having it actually be referred to the female.
But to you and to your friends, meaning to the people who
learn תורה Torah *Torah*. שנאמר *She-ne'emar*, all Rome gathered all the wealth
of the world, but ultimately it's all going to go to the
people who who involve themselves in תורה Torah, *Torah*. שנאמר *She-ne'emar*, as
the verse says, סחרה ואתננה קודש להשם לא יאצר Lo ye'atzer ולא
יחסן כי ליושבים לפני השם יהיה *Sachrah v'esnanah kodesh l'Hashem lo ye'atzer
v'lo yeichasen ki l'yoshvim lifnei Hashem yihyeh*. Its hire and its hire
and it's אתננה *esnanah*, which is also used in the case of
like אתנן זונה *esnan zonah*, like hire for prostitution, but it could
just mean its wealth and its and its hire. קודש להשם *Kodesh
l'Hashem* will be sanctified to God. לא יאצר ולא יחסן *Lo ye'atzer
v'lo yeichasen*, it will not be stored up and it will not
be kept in treasure. כי ליושבים לפני השם יהיה *Ki l'yoshvim lifnei
Hashem yihyeh*, it would all be for those that dwell before God.
So all the treasure and the wealth that was gathered by Rome
will ultimately be for those who study. study Torah. מאי לא יאצר
what does it mean it will not be kept stored up? תני
רב יוסף Tani Rav Yosef לא יאצר זה בית אוצר zeh beit
otzar that's a storehouse of grain. So לא יחסן Lo yechasen also
won't be kept in treasure, in a treasury, זה בית גניזה zeh
beit genizah that is a treasury of like gold and silver. So
all of those things, the grain, the gold, the silver, ultimately it'll
all go to the Torah scholars. מאי כי ליושבים לפני השם Mai
ki layoshvim lifnei Hashem what does it mean it'll go to those
that sit before God? What specifically is indicated by that? אמר רבי
אלעזר Amar Rabbi Elazar זה המכיר מקום חבירו בישיבה zeh hamakir mekom
chaveiro b'yeshiva
that's somebody who is so regular in the בית מדרש Beit Midrash
that he knows where everybody sits. This is where so-and-so sits, that's
where so-and-so sits. Okay, so that's יושבים לפני השם. yoshvim lifnei Hashem.
Could also mean, although that's the way the רשב"ם Rashbam says it,
you're so, you're a regular so you know everybody's מקום קבוע. makom
kavua. Could also mean that you respect everybody's מקום. makom. You don't
go ahead and...
I remember Rabbi Berman told me once a story, you know, at
Ramat Orah which is on 110th Street. So now I think it's
very, you know, it's quite popular with Columbia, whatever, but anyway there
was a time when like there was very few people went there
and he says that his wife Shelly on one, I think it
was like a שבת Shabbos day went to the שול shul there
was absolutely nobody in the whole women's section. She sat down in
a seat. An hour later a woman comes over to her and
says, "You're in my seat."
So, anyway, alright.
That's happened to me.
It has?
Yeah. Anyway, alright.
Right. So if you're really regular in a place, you know where
everybody sits even the people that don't only come once a, you
know, once a year. You know where everybody's מקום makom is. Okay.
המכיר מקום חבירו בישיבה. hamakir mekom chaveiro b'yeshiva. איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri
some say אמר רבי אלעזר amar Rabbi Elazar זה המקבל פני חבירו
בישיבה. zeh hamikabel pnei chaveiro b'yeshiva.
So it means that you, you know, you welcome, you're always the
one there. Anybody that walks in, you're the one always there welcoming
שלום עליכם, shalom aleichem, whatever, because you are the fixture of the
בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. That's who you are. But again I will
say that in addition to the idea of being a fixture in
the place, both of those ideas of מכיר makir and מקבל mikabel
also show that sense of respect for the other people that are
there. You know, it's interesting to sort of acknowledge that, that it's
not just that all you're concerned about is your learning. You're aware
of the other people in the בית מדרש Beit Midrash as well
and you don't sit in their place and when they walk in
you don't say I can't talk to you I'm busy learning and
you welcome them. So it's an interesting balance between the sense that
you're always before God, but you're always יושבים yoshvim in the plural,
you're always also, you know, sensitive to the community and the other
people that are there as well. So מאי ולמכסה עתיק mai ul'michaseh
atik that's the end of the פסוק. pasuk? It says it'll be
for those that are before God and that cover up the ancient
of days למכסה עתיק, l'michaseh atik, what does that mean the ancient?
So זה המכסה דברים שכיסה עתיק יומין. zeh hamichaseh devarim shekissah atik
yomin. So עתיק יומין atik yomin is understood to refer to God
based on a פסוק pasuk in Daniel, the ancient of days. So
this is the one that covers up things that God has covered
up. ומאי ניהו סתרי תורה? umai nihu sitrei Torah? Those are the
hidden things of the Torah, like the hidden Kabbalistic secrets about מעשה
מרכבה, Ma'aseh Merkavah, so you do your responsibility, you don't go ahead
and reveal things that should not be revealed. ואיכא דאמרי v'ika d'amri
some say זה המגלה דברים שכיסה עתיק יומין. zeh hamigaleh devarim shekissah
atik yomin. You reveal, you actually reveal things that have been hidden
up, but things you're supposed to reveal. ומאי ניהו umai nihu and
what are these? טעמי תורה, ta'amei Torah, not סתרי תורה sitrei Torah
but טעמי תורה. ta'amei Torah. So the difference is סתרי תורה sitrei
Torah are these like, you know,
very mysteries and they're the very like, you know, they're the Kabbalistic
or, you know, like I said מעשה מרכבה, Ma'aseh Merkavah, the things
that are, what's that word for them?
Not esoteric... you know, this esoteric knowledge that's not, cannot... is powerful
and can't be shared. טעמי תורה ta'amei Torah are trying to get,
dig deeper in like what's the meaning of this. You know, it's
not the hidden mysteries, it's like, you know, whether it's a הלכה,
halacha, whether it's a story, you want to understand what's its meaning.
You know, the narratives in the Torah have a lot that aren't
said. You know, that's what מדרשים Midrashim is, that's what מפרשים mefarshim
is, that's why people write פרשה שיעורים, parsha shiurim, you know, you
want to understand what's it all about. And the same about the
הלכות halachot and that's a type of investigation that is not meant
not to be discovered, it's just not explicit in the Torah and
that's a type of exploration and thinking and reflecting we're supposed to
do about the מצוות mitzvot and the narratives in the Torah. מהרש"א
Maharsha has an interesting point. He says what about the fact that
the גמרא Gemara says in other places that the Torah did not
reveal the טעמי המצוות ta'amei ha-mitzvot because if it tells you the
reason for the מצוות mitzvot then you're going to say, "Oh, this
reason doesn't apply to
me." Like why it says לא ירבה לו נשים פן יסור לבבו,
lo yarbeh lo nashim pen yasur levavo, so Shlomo said, "I can
have many wives and they won't יסור לבבו" yasur levavo and he
was נכשל. nichshal. So the Torah wasn't... didn't reveal its reasons. So
he says, "How come here it says you're supposed to reveal the
reasons?" So one thing is he says maybe טעמי תורה ta'amei Torah
is different than טעמי מצוות. ta'amei mitzvot. But the other thing he
says is, and I thought this was fascinating, he says, "No." He
says, "If the Torah reveals it, it's dangerous. If you reveal it,
it's
not." Well, maybe it's because of this, maybe it's because of that,
but you don't hopefully have the arrogance to think, I know exactly
why this מצוה mitzvah was said and therefore I can make decision
X, Y, and Z. If the תורה Torah says it, then you
downplay the מצוה mitzvah and you only say it's all about the
reason. But you're supposed to work to discover the reason, but it
comes with the recognition that at the end of the day, it's
just your speculation. So I think it's a very beautiful מהרש"א Maharsha
about that difference. Because it is true on the one hand you
do have a whole so much effort has gone into understanding what's
the reason of the מצוות, mitzvot, what's the reasons of the תורה,
how do we understand them, and at the same time it has
to come coupled with this humility. So, all right, now the גמרא
continues. אמר רב כהנא משום רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי: Amar Rav Kahana
mishum Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yose: מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, what's meant by
the verse?
Again, אמר רב כהנא Amar Rav Kahana in the name of רבי
ישמעאל Yishmael. ברבי יוסי. What's meant by the verse למנצח מזמור לדוד
זמרו, Lamnatzeach mizmor l'David zamru,
to the למנצח menatzeach
a song of David sing. למי שנוצחין אותו ושמח, L'mi shenotzchin oto
v'samayach, to the one who when one is victorious over him, he's
happy. So what's למנצח, menatzeach, לא נוצח lo notzeach but למנצח? menatzeach?
Causes others. So again as opposed to reading this as some type
of a musical, of a play of some type of music to
be played, they read it from the word ניצחון, nitzachon, victory, one
who causes others to be victorious. למי שנוצחין אותו ושמח, L'mi shenotzchin
oto v'samayach, so it's to God who's למנצח, menatzeach, causes others, us
to be victorious.
בוא וראה שלא כמידת הקדוש ברוך הוא מידת בשר ודם, Bo u're'eh
shelo k'middat haKadosh Baruch Hu middat basar v'dam,
come see that God's way is not the way of flesh and
blood. בשר ודם נוצחין אותו ועצב, Basar v'dam notzchin oto v'atzayve, a
normal case of flesh and blood you are victorious over a person
and he is sad, he is distraught. אבל הקדוש ברוך הוא נוצחין
אותו ושמח, Aval haKadosh Baruch Hu notzchin oto v'samayach, God when you
are victorious over him, he's happy. שנאמר ויאמר להשמידם לולי משה בחירו
עמד בפרץ לפניו. Shene'emar Vayomer l'hashmidam lulei Moshe bechiro amad baperetz lefanav.
God wanted to wipe them out,
were it not that משה בחירו Moshe bechiro stood in the breach
לפניו in God's presence. So you see משה Moshe went ahead, he
fought against God, he was victorious, and משה בחירו, Moshe bechiro, it
was a good thing obviously. משה Moshe is the בחירו, bechiro, the
chosen one. You're supposed to have that. So again, this in a
way also evokes those stories we just read a minute ago about
the שר של יעבץ, sar shel Yavetz, hey God, what about paying
me back? גבריאל says everybody's arguing with God, the angels are arguing
with God. So now we see that even we're supposed to argue
with God and God wants it, that's מנצח. menatzeach. So it's a
very, while the sort of the whole idea of the angelic retinue
is hard to relate to, but to see how from that דף
daf to this דף it translates into a relationship we have with
God, I think can be very powerful. אמר רב כהנא משום רבי
ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. Amar Rav Kahana mishum Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yose.
אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש משום רבי יהודה נשיאה: Amar Rabbi Shimon
ben Lakish mishum Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah: מאי דכתיב, mai d'chsiv, what's meant
by the verse? וידי אדם מתחת כנפיהם, V'yedei adam mitachat kanfeihem, the
hands of a man are underneath their wings, these angelic wings, the
vision in the beginning of יחזקאל. Yechezkel. ידו כתיב, Yado ketiv, not
it says ידי yedei but actually it's written with a vav, ידו,
yado, his hand. Whose hand? ידו של הקדוש ברוך הוא, Yado shel
haKadosh Baruch Hu, this is God's hand. שפרוסה תחת כנפי החיות, Sheperusha
tachat kanfei hachayot, that it's God's hand is stretching under the wings
of the angels that are like surrounding God and keeping God as
a way,
distant from us, shielded from us, כדי לקבל בעלי תשובה k'dei l'kabel
ba'alei teshuvah in order to receive those who come back and repent.
מיד, I don't know, it looks like a מיד whatever, מיד מידת
הדין miyad midat hadin or מפני מידת הדין mipnei midat hadin to
sort of, in spite of the divine sense of divine justice, the
attribute of justice, here is the attribute of רחמים. rachamim. So again,
this is a fascinating idea, this sort of repeating theme like before
when we say God, לך אנו, l'cha anu, we are yours and
therefore you should save us, the sense about this very special intimate
relationship that God has with us and that breaks through these types
of barriers. On the one hand, it's such a close relationship that
he wants us to argue with him and he wants us to
challenge him. A minute ago it was just the angels, now it's
we're doing it, and a type of relationship that even though he's
supposed to like his angels are trying to protect him, he wants
to ensure that we have that connection, he's stretching out his hand.
אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: כל כסף וזהב
שבעולם, Kol kessef v'zahav sheba'olam, now all the gold and silver, we'll
see how this will tie back in a minute.
יוסף לקטו והביאו למצרים. Yosef likto v'hevi'o l'Mitzrayim. יוסף Yosef gathered, before
we mentioned the Romans had it, so this is picking up on
that theme, יוסף Yosef gathered all the gold and silver and brought
it to Egypt. שנאמר וילקט יוסף את כל הכסף הנמצא בארץ מצרים
ובארץ כנען. Shene'emar Vayelaket Yosef et kol hakessef hanimtzah b'eretz Mitzrayim u'b'eretz
Kena'an. אין לי אלא שבארץ מצרים ושבארץ כנען, Ein li ela sheb'eretz
Mitzrayim v'sheb'eretz Kena'an, I only know in Egypt and in Canaan. בשאר
ארצות מניין, B'sha'ar aratzot minayin, how about other lands? תלמוד לומר וכל
הארץ באו מצרימה, Talmud lomar V'chol ha'aretz ba'u Mitzraymah, all the lands
came to Egypt. וכשעלו ישראל ממצרים, U'cheshe'alu Yisrael miMitzrayim, now when we
left Egypt, העלו עמהם, he'elu immahem, they took with them, we took
all the gold and silver in the entire world, which we said
before was in Rome but now we're going earlier in history, we
took it out of Egypt, it had all been brought to Egypt,
we took it with us. שנאמר וינצלו את מצרים, Shene'emar Vayenatzlu et
Mitzrayim, they sort of stripped Egypt. מאי וינצלו, Mai vayenatzlu, what does
וינצלו vayenatzlu mean? רב
אסי אמר עשאוה כמצודה, Rav Assi amar assu'ah k'metzudah, we're reading וינצלו.
vayenatzlu. like a מצודה, metzuda, like a דלית dalet instead of a
למד, lamed, they made it like a bird trap שאין בו דגן
she'ein bo dagan that had completely been emptied of its grain. You
put grain so the birds will come and peck at the grain.
We had to sort of swipe the grain out without getting caught
in the trap. רבי שמעון אומר רבי שמעון בן לקיש אומר כמצולה
שאין בה דגים, k'metzula she'ein bah dagim, like וינצלו vayinatzlu keeping the
למד, lamed, like a pond that has no fish. We completely emptied
it out of all of its wealth. והיה מונח עד רחבעם v'hayah
munach ad Rechavam and it was staying, it stayed in the hands
of בני ישראל until the time of רחבעם, Rechavam,
the son of שלמה. Shlomo. בא שישק מלך מצרים ונטלה מרחבעם. Ba
Shishak melech Mitzrayim v'netalah me'Rechavam. Shishak came and took it all from
Rechavam, שנאמר ויהי בשנה החמישית למלך רחבעם עלה שישק מלך מצרים על
ירושלים ויקח את אוצרות בית ה' ואת אוצרות בית המלך. Shene'emar vayihi
bashanah hachamishit lamelech Rechavam alah Shishak melech Mitzrayim al Yerushalayim vayikach et
otzrot beit Hashem v'et otzrot beit hamelech. He took all of the
storehouses and all of the treasure houses.
So the sequel, he took the money back.
Yeah exactly, the Egyptians took the money back. We're not done though.
בא זרח מלך כוש ונטלה משישק. Ba Zerach melech Kush u'netalah me'Shishak.
Came Zerach the king of Kush and took it from Shishak. That's
not in the פסוקים, pesukim the רש"י Rashi says that's just tradition.
בא אסא ונטלה מזרח מלך כוש. Ba Asa u'netalah mi'Zerach melech Kush.
So Asa came and he did war against the king of Kush,
which is in the פסוקים, pesukim and he took it from Kush.
ושיגרה להדרדימון בן טברימון v'shigrah l'Hadardimon ben Tavrimon and sent it to
Hadardimon ben Tavrimon, which was the king of ארם Aram to protect
them from being attacked by
בעשא מלך ישראל. Baasha melech Yisrael. באו בני עמון ונטלוה מהדרדימון בן
טברימון. Ba'u Bnei Amon u'netaluha me'Hadardimon ben Tavrimon. So then the Ammonites
came and took it from him.
בא יהושפט ונטלה מבני עמון Ba Yehoshaphat u'netalah mi'Bnei Amon because we
actually we have פסוקים pesukim about Yehoshaphat going to war against בני
עמון. Bnei Amon. והיה מונח עד אחז v'hayah munach ad Achaz and
it was in the hands of the
Israelite kings until Achaz, or the Judean kings until Achaz. בא סנחריב
ונטלה מאחז. Ba Sancheriv u'netalah me'Achaz. Came Sancheriv and took it from
Achaz. בא חזקיהו ונטלה מסנחריב. Ba Chizkiyahu u'netalah mi'Sancheriv. So that was,
I'm sorry, Achaz was the Israelite king, so Sancheriv took it. Came
Chizkiyahu the Judean king and took it from when the angel wiped
out Sancheriv's armies. So then presumably we came and we looted the
armies and we took back all of the wealth, assuming they had
all their wealth with them when they went to war. והיה מונח
עד צדקיהו v'hayah munach ad Tzidkiyahu and it was in the hands
of the Judean kings until the time of
Tzidkiyahu. באו כשדיים ונטלוה מצדקיהו u'ba'u Kasdim u'netaluha mi'Tzidkiyahu and they took
it from Tzidkiyahu. באו פרסיים ונטלוה מכשדיים. Ba'u Parsiyim u'netaluha mi'Kasdim. Then
we know the Persians took over, you know, the sort of empire
from the Kasdim. באו יווניים ונטלוה מפרסיים. Ba'u Yevanim u'netaluha mi'Parsiyim. Then
came the Greeks, Alexander and so on, and took it over from
the Persians. באו רומיים ונטלוה מיד יווניים. Ba'u Romiyim u'netaluha mi-yad Yevanim.
And then the Romans came and took it from the Greeks. And
that's how we mentioned before that all the wealth is now in
the hands of the Romans. ועדיין מונח ברומי v'adayin munach b'Romi
and it's still in Rome, which by the way is a nice
closure to the idea of remember the story? And who's going to
get all that wealth in the end? It'll go back to the
people who are sitting in ישיבה. yeshiva. So in a way we're
sort of saying it came from us as well. Now, it came
from us because we took it from the Egyptians, but fine, the
Egyptians took it from the rest of the world and at least
that taking the wealth from the Egyptians was already prophesied and that
was sort of the source. So in the end it's all going
to come back to us in the end anyway.
The Jews are the money
lenders.
אוי אוי אוי. Oy oy oy. אמר רב חמא ברבי חנינא, Amar
Rav Chama b'Rabbi Chanina, שלוש מטמוניות הטמין יוסף במצרים. shalosh matmoniyot hitmin
Yosef b'Mitzrayim. So on this theme of wealth in Egypt,
three treasures Yosef buried in
Egypt. אחת נתגלתה לקרח. achat nitgaltah l'Korach. One was revealed to Korach
and that's how Korach got so
wealthy. ואחת נתגלתה לאנטונינוס בן אסוירוס. v'achat nitgaltah l'Antuninus ben Asveirus. And
one was revealed to Anthony the son of Severus. So I was
looking on the web, I don't know anybody associated Anthony of the
Anthony and Cleopatra with that he was a son of Severus. Severus
was the name of a Caesar though, wasn't he? Yeah. And so
was he after? Was he the Caesar after Anthony?
I don't know. Anyway, okay, Tali will tell
us. ואחת גנוזה לצדיקים לעתיד לבוא. v'achat genuzah l'tzadikim l'atid lavo. And
one, so it's interesting, not like all the wealth and it constantly
was changing hands, it's all going to go back to us. No,
a third, a third, and a third. A third the צדיקים tzadikim
will get לעתיד לבוא. l'asid lavo, עושר שמור לבעליו לרעתו. osher shamur
l've'alav l'ra'ato. Now here's a פסוק. pasuk Wealth that is held, protected
for the owner and ultimately is for their evil, for their undoing.
אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש זה עושרו של קרח. Amar Rabbi Shimon
ben Lakish zeh oshro shel Korach. That's the wealth of Korach. His
wealth made him, you know, haughty and made him think that he
could go ahead and rebel against משה Moshe, and ultimately it came
to destroy him. ואת כל היקום אשר ברגליהם. v'et kol hayekum asher
b'ragleihem.
All of the wealth that was swallowed up, it said all of
the wealth that was on their at their feet. אמר רבי אלעזר
זה ממונו של אדם, Amar Rabbi Elazar zeh mamono shel adam, שמעמידו
על רגליו. she'ma'amido al raglav.
This is a person's money
that makes him stand up on his feet, that gives him a
sense of dignity and of importance and that's what made Korach feel
again, you know, pride and able to challenge Moshe, and in the
end it was all swallowed up. אמר רבי לוי, Amar Rabbi Levi,
משא שלוש מאות פרדות לבנות היו מפתחות בית גנזיו של קרח. masa
shalosh me'ot pardot levanot hayu mafteichot beit genaziv shel Korach.
So before we had 365 for the Romans of their warehouses, the
burdens of 300 white mules were the keys of the treasure house
of Korach. burden of 300 white mules was the was was
was not the treasures of קרח Korach but the keys, the keys
to his treasure houses took 300 of these white mules to carry,
it was their load, the where are we? שכוח Shakoach וכולו אקלידי
וקליפי דגלדא נינהו, vechulo aklidi veklifi degalda ninhu, they were all keys
and locks set of leather, they were all light. So we weren't
even heavy keys and so 300 300 mules carry them and how
but you can only imagine how big the actual treasure was. Yes,
Charlie.
One possibility for Antoninus, Marcus
Caesar Marcus Aurelius Antoninus Augustus who is believed to be the one
who always had the conversation with רבי, his father, grandfather, and great
grandfather were all named Marcus Antoninus Verus.
Aha, so wait that's a Severus but his name he was Antoninus?
His full name as emperor was Caesar Marcus Aurelius Antoninus Augustus.
So there was an Antoninus there. Okay.
And his father and the previous empire emperor was Antoninus Pius, so
that's another possibility. Now we know.
Okay, moving on. Okay. All right, אמר רב שמעון בן לקיש Amar
Rav Shimon ben Lakish אמר רב יוחנן Amar Rav Yochanan back to
פסוקים pesukim in הלל. Hallel. Okay. Back to פסוקים pesukim in הלל.
Hallel? אודך השם כי עניתני, Odecha Hashem ki anisani,
I will thank God because you've answered me. אמר דוד Amar David
אבן מאסו הבונים היתה לראש פינה, Even ma'asu habonim hayesa lerosh pina,
I'm sorry actually I said that wrong. אודך כי עניתני, Odecha ki
anisani, I will thank you because you have answered me. אמר דוד.
Amar David. That's what דוד David said. In what context? Probably when
he was fighting against גלית, Golyas, but דוד David had enough צרות,
tzaros, he could have said it any time. Anyway, אבן מאסו הבונים
היתה לראש פינה, Even ma'asu habonim hayesa lerosh pina, the stone cast
away by the builders became the cornerstone. אמר ישי. Amar Yishai. That's
what ישי Yishai said. מאת השם היתה זאת Me'eis Hashem haysa zos
because דוד David was the youngest of the children and so on
also the מהרש"א brings in the whole מדרש Midrash about how דוד'ס
David's lineage was completely challenged. How could דוד David be a king?
He descends from רות המואביה Rus HaMoaviya and so on so that's
מאסו הבונים, ma'asu habonim, he actually says plays on the
בונים bonim right אל תקרי בנייך אלא בונייך, al tikra banayich ela
bonayich, so that it means
that תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim were despising דוד, David, oh he's from
רות המואביה, Rus HaMoaviya, he can't be he can't be a king.
So it's מאסו הבונים היתה לראש פינה ma'asu habonim hayesa lerosh pina
אמר ישי. Amar Yishai. מאת השם היתה זאת Me'eis Hashem haysa zos
אמרו אחיו. amru echav. Okay
again what's the moment when he became king? When he won over
גלית? Golyas? The רשב"ם also says because it says at the end
of it מאת השם היתה זאת, Me'eis Hashem haysa zos, what's the
end of the פסוק? pasuk היא נפלאת בעינינו. hi niflas be'eineinu. היא
נפלאת בעינינו Hi niflas be'eineinu
in the plural so it's אמרו אחיו. amru echav. אמרו אחיו Amru
echav זה היום עשה השם ze hayom asa Hashem אמר שמואל amar
Shmuel
when דוד David presumably was chosen and שמואל Shmuel is told to
go to anoint him. אנא השם הושיעה נא Anna Hashem hoshia na
אמרו אחיו. amru echav. אנא השם הצליחה נא Anna Hashem hatzlicha na
אמר דוד. amar David. Again
it's not clear what stage again fighting גלית, Golyas, what's going on.
ברוך הבא בשם השם Baruch haba beshem Hashem אמר ישי. amar Yishai.
ברכנוכם מבית השם Berachnuchem mibeis Hashem אמר שמואל. amar Shmuel. קל השם
ויאר לנו Keil Hashem vaya'er lanu אמרו כולם. amru chulam. אסרו חג
בעבותים Isru chag ba'avosim אמר שמואל amar Shmuel
because at least okay about the bringing sacrifice. אלי אתה ואודך Eli
ata ve'odeka אמר דוד. omar David. אלוקי ארוממך Elokei aromemeka אמר כולם.
amar chulam. I don't know
what to make of this because it doesn't give us any context
but what you could imagine by the way is and one does
wonder to what degree was some of this like enacted when they
were saying the הלל? Hallel, Like did people have parts and were
people actually saying this? You see what they're trying to do is
they're trying to take this very sort of just generic praise and
bring it to life almost as like a type of a
play and we had that before right about the לא לנו לא
לנו lo lanu lo lanu and you sort of wonder how much
some this might have been somewhat enacted when they were actually saying
the הלל, Hallel, yes.
We should do that at the בית מדרש bais medrash sometime soon.
Oh yeah, I am sure that they would get into that. I
totally can imagine everybody dresses up and we all have parts. Okay
anyway תנן התם. tnan hasam. Now we turn to a little bit
of a halachic discussion. מקום שנהגו לכפול יכפול. Makom shenahagu lechepol yichpol.
What? I know.
So this is really from a discussion in סוכה Sukkah where it
discusses הלל, Hallel, the place where they double things up in the
הלל, Hallel right we double some פסוקים pesukim right אודך השם
כי עניתני, odecha Hashem ki anisani, whatever, at the end we do
all this doubling up of פסוקים psukim? which is not in the
original פסוקים psukim. as written, you double. לפשוט Liphshot where they say
it straight without doubling, לפשוט, liphshot, you say it straight. לברך אחריו
יברך Levarech acharav yevarech כי כברך ki kevarech if you have a
מנהג minhag to make the ברכה bracha at the end you make
it, right so we obviously do we actually got through just saying
how on ליל סדר leil seder it's very clear we make a
ברכה bracha of course which ברכה bracha but not in all places
did they make a ברכה bracha at the end but the place
that they do you do it. הכל כמנהג המדינה Hakol keminhag hamedina
everything follows the custom of the place. אמר אביי Amar Abaye לא
שנו אלא אחריו lo shanu ela acharav that debate or that difference
of customs of making a ברכה bracha afterwards that's only a final
ברכה. bracha. אבל לפניו Aval lefanav before it מצוה לברך mitzvah levarech
you have to make a ברכה bracha you make a ברכה bracha
before every מצוה mitzvah okay דאמר רב יהודה de-amar Rav Yehuda
by the way it's a little bit ironic because on ליל סדר
everybody makes a ברכה bracha at the end and not at the
beginning but he is saying that in a normal saying of הלל
Hallel, whatever the debate is But he is saying that in a
normal saying of הלל, Hallel. whatever the debate is about the end,
we all make it at the beginning.
But what about at the end?
ברכה Bracha should be at the
end? Alright, we'll talk about it, I'll get back to that. דאמר
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda אמר שמואל Shmuel כל מצוות mitzvos מברך mevarach
עליהן aleihen עובר לעשייתן. over la'asiyasan All מצוות mitzvos you have to
do before you have to make the ברכה bracha before you perform
them. מאי משמע דעובר לישנא דאקדומי הוא? Mai mashma d'over lishna d'akdumi
hu? There is a גמרא that repeats itself a number of times
in a number of different מסכתות. masechtos. How do you know that
the language of, right, we start way at the beginning of the
מסכת, right? Brings us back to that. How do you know that
the idea עובר over means before you do it, עובר over before
you do it? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק דכתיב וירץ אחימעץ דרך
הככר ויעבור את הכושי. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak d'chsiv vayaratz Achima'atz
derech hakikar vaya'avor es haCushi.
אחימעץ Achima'atz ran the way of the valley and he passed in
front of the Ethiopian. So עבר avor means to pass in front
of. So עובר over לעשייתן la'asiyasan. means the ברכה bracha has to
proceed and come in front of the doing. אביי אמר מהכא והוא
עבר לפניהם, Abaye amar mehacha vehu avar lifneihem, he passed in front
of them. איכא דאמרי מהכא ויעבור מלכם לפניהם והשם בראשם Ika d'amri
mehacha vaya'avor malkam lifneihem v'Hashem berosham and their king passes in front
of them. So it's interesting by the way about thinking about that
image about passing in front because you know when you run in
front of somebody you almost like announce their coming and the ברכה
עובר לעשייתן bracha over la'asiyasan it passes in front of the ברכה,
bracha, it announces and proclaims and gives identity to the מצוה. mitzvah.
Now I will say though, or you know, we'll read a little
bit and then I'll finish. תניא, Tanya, we learned in a ברייתא,
braisa, רבי כופל בדברים, Rebbi kofel bidvarim, רבי would repeat certain verses.
רבי אלעזר בן פרטא מוסיף בדברים, Rebbi Elazar ben Parta mosif bidvarim,
he would add. What does it mean add? He'd add something extraneous
to the פסוקים? pesukim
So מאי מוסיף, mai mosif, what does it mean he would add?
אמר אביי מוסיף לכפול, Amar Abaye mosif lichpol, it means he would
do more doubling than רבי would do. מאודך למטה. Me'odecha l'mata. He
would double from the פסוק of אודך השם כי עניתני, Odecha Hashem
ki anisani, which is what we say right before the אנא השם
הושיעה נא. Ana Hashem hoshia na. The רשב"ם said רבי would only
do the doubling from ברוך הבא בשם השם, Baruch haba b'shem Hashem,
but he did more doubling. Okay. דרש רב עוירא, Darash Rav Avira,
רב עוירא Rav Avira explicated, זימנין אמרה משמיה דרב וזימנין אמרה משמיה
דרב אשי, zimnin amrah mishmeih d'Rav v'zimnin amrah mishmeih d'Rav Ashi, or
דרב אסי, de'Rav Assi, מאי דכתיב, what's meant by the verse ויגדל
הילד ויגמל, vayaratz Achima'atz derech hakikar vayigdal hayeled vayigamel, the child grew
up and he was weaned? So there you go, right, this week's
פרשה, parsha, right? עתיד הקדוש ברוך הוא לעשות סעודה לצדיקים ביום שיגמל
חסדו לזרעו של יצחק. Asid Hakadosh Baruch Hu la'asos seuda latzadikim beyom
sheyigamel chasdo l'zaro shel Yitzchak. So not just about יצחק Yitzchak growing
up and being weaned, but God in the end will make a
סעודה, seuda, ויעש אברהם משתה גדול, vaya'as Avraham mishteh gadol, so it
won't be אברהם Avraham that does the משתה גדול, mishteh gadol, God
will make a משתה גדול mishteh gadol when we will be not
weaned, but גומל חסד, gomel chesed, when God will ultimately pay us
back in the future לעתיד לבוא, in the time of משיח, Mashiach,
God is going to make a סעודה seuda for everyone. Okay. לאחר
שאוכלים ושותים, Le'achar she'ochlim v'shosim, after everybody eats and drinks, נותנים לו
לאברהם אבינו כוס של ברכה, nosnim lo l'Avraham Avinu kos shel bracha,
now the question, who do we give to, to lead benching? So
they give it to אברהם Avraham לברך. l'varech. ואמר להן, V'amar lahen,
he said, no, I only had מזונות. mezonos. ואמר להן איני מברך,
V'amar lahen eini mevarach,
he says, I'm not going to lead the benching, שיצא ממני ישמעאל.
sheyatza mimeni Yishmael. I'm not
entitled. I had ישמעאל. Yishmael, I was not the one to represent,
I'm not here the one to represent the entire Jewish people. So
אמרו לו ליצחק, amru lo l'Yitzchak, they said יצחק, Yitzchak, טול וברך,
tol u'varech, you make the ברכה. bracha. אמר להן איני מברך, Amar
lahen eini mevarach, I won't do it, שיצא ממני עשו. sheyatza mimeni
Esav. עשו came from me, so I'm not pure, totally pure, or
again it's not that I did anything wrong, but somehow I'm not
the one to represent כל ישראל Klal Yisrael here. אמרו לו ליעקב,
Amru lo l'Yaakov, said to יעקב, Yaakov, טול וברך, tol u'varech, you
do it. אמר להן איני מברך, Amar lahen eini mevarach, I won't,
שנשאתי שתי אחיות בחייהן, shenasasi shtei achayos bechayeihen, I married two sisters
when they were both alive, שעתידה תורה לאוסרן עלי, she'asida Torah le'osran
alai, the תורה will make it forbidden to me. Again, did I
do anything wrong? No. But somehow in this time, you know, now
at the אחרית הימים, acharis hayamim, I am not the best representative
of, you know, of כל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. Interesting. He's building up
some interesting tension. Who are we going to pick? Everybody's got something
wrong with them. So אמרו לו למשה, amru lo l'Moshe, טול וברך,
tol u'varech, so they said to משה, Moshe lead the benching. אמר
להן איני מברך, Amar lahen eini mevarach, I won't, שלא זכיתי ליכנס
לארץ ישראל. shelo zachisi l'hikanes l'Eretz Yisrael. I did not merit to
go into ישראל. Again, not like, so what, he didn't do anything
wrong, wasn't your fault. לא בחיי ולא במותי, Lo bechayai v'lo b'mosi,
not in my life and not in my death. Okay, so again,
not that he did anything wrong, but if the ideal of ישראל
is, you know, the Jewish people living in the land of ישראל,
I don't fully represent that. I represent more of a גלות galus
or more of a transition stage. אמרו לו ליהושע, Amru lo l'Yehoshua,
טול וברך, tol u'varech, so they said יהושע, Yehoshua, you make the
blessing. אמר להן איני מברך, Amar lahen eini mevarach, no, I won't,
שלא זכיתי לבן, shelo zachisi l'ven, דכתיב, יהושע בן נון, Yehoshua bin
Nun, נון בנו יהושע בנו, Nun bno Yehoshua bno, so when it
lists genealogies it says יהושע Yehoshua and נון Nun and יהושע Yehoshua
and it doesn't go beyond that. He didn't have any children. So
how could I represent the whole continuity of the people if I
myself had no children?
I thought he had daughters.
That, would be interesting. I don't know, I didn't check the פסוקים.
Yeah, I don't know where what you're basing that on. You can
get back to us on that. So אמרו לו לדוד, amru lo
l'David, they said to דוד, David, טול וברך, tol u'varech, you make
the blessing. אמר להן אני אברך ולי נאה לברך. Amar lahen ani
avarech v'li na'eh l'varech. Oh, I'll make the blessing. Okay, good choice.
I'll make the blessing. Exactly, he didn't say it, דוד David had
a lot of things he could have said that he wasn't appropriate.
So לי נאה לברך, li na'eh l'varech, שנאמר כוס ישועות אשא ובשם
השם אקרא, shene'emar kos yeshuos esa u'v'shem Hashem ekra, to end us
with another פסוק from the הלל. Hallel. But again, what you could
say obviously דוד David was a flawed. person as well as was
everybody in תנ״ך. Tanakh.
He didn't merit to build the Temple.
But what I guess, so the absence of the Temple is interesting,
but I guess what you could say here is that if we're
looking at this idea of עתיד לבוא, Atid Lavo, which is about
משיח, which is about the resurgence of מלכות בית דוד, Malchus Beis
Dovid, and the whole idea משה didn't go into the
land, and it's something that sort of represents Jewish sovereignty and Jewish
pride, and it's all about ישראל, it's not about ישמעאל, it's not
about
עשו, so
you sort of understand that that sense of our national Jewish identity,
Israelite God, whatever, religious identity sort of distilled in the person of
דוד. Dovid. He's the one we focus on when we think about
messianic times.
Right, so does this restatement in any way connected to the concern
that increasingly communities have had for messianic singers repeating פסוקים and you
shouldn't repeat words when you're saying them?
Yeah, this
is an undercurrent of that. It's never clear that it's such a
strictly הלכתית halachic issue but people are very מחמיר. machmir.
Right, it also depends on what context are you repeating. Like, are
you repeating in שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei where there's very much like
in a context of a ברכה bracha and we discussed the other
day about changing a ברכה bracha etc., or are you saying in
a sense in which... but yes, I think look it could go
either way. You could say the fact that here it has to
give license for you to double suggests that in other cases you
can't be doubling. And also I think there's a difference of repeating
a פסוק as a sort of stretching out a melody and an
individual word, but yes, there's a whole literature on that. I'm not
sure how much it references it, but I would agree the fact
that here it has to give license to double indicates that in
general it's something to be cautious of. I would say that again,
this whole idea of doubling, like this idea of the, like I
almost said the enacting of various parts, one does imagine that they
probably had some interesting things going on when they were doing the
הלל. Hallel The issue, I do want to say one thing about
the issue about the ברכה bracha beforehand and how it gets insisted
and how it's not necessarily obvious because it gets to this issue
about to what degree is הלל Hallel, seen as a מצוה mitzvah
and to what degree is it seen as תפילה, tefillah, right? And
for example, there's a מצוה mitzvah we say every day during דאווענינג.
davening. What's the מצוה mitzvah we say every day during דאווענינג? davening?
שמע. Shema. Do we say אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על קריאת שמע?
Asher kideshanu b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu al krias Shema? No. We do have something
called ברכות קריאת שמע, Birkos Krias Shema, but if you think about
it, the ברכות קריאת שמע Birkos Krias Shema are ברכות brachos that
draw out the themes of שמע, Shema, right? So the ברכה bracha
about יוצר המאורות, Yotzer HaMeoros, if you want, draws out the theme
of ה׳ אלהינו ה׳ אחד, Hashem Elokeinu Hashem Echad, the universal God.
And certainly the next one about אוהב עמו ישראל, Ohev Amo Yisrael,
which is שמע ישראל ה׳ אלהינו ה׳ אחד, Shema Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu
Hashem Echad, it's about our relationship. Those ברכות, brachos, but they're not
אשר קדשנו במצותיו. asher kideshanu b'mitzvosav. They are ברכות brachos of שמע
Shema as part of תפילה tefillah and therefore they become an expansion
of the תפילה tefillah itself. So by the הלל, Hallel there's definitely
a חידוש chidush of saying אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על קריאת ההלל
asher kideshanu b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu al krias haHallel that you make it into
a מעשה מצוה maaseh mitzvah and as opposed to a
ברכה bracha that sort of expands it as a type of a
תפילה. tefillah. So the fact that the גמרא says oh, by the
way, of course you say a ברכה bracha before because you say
a ברכה bracha before every מצוה mitzvah is not so obvious that
we would do that in something that, first of all, it's only
rabbinic, well, according to the רמב״ן Ramban it is a biblical מצוה
mitzvah as we discussed, but anyway, but something that is being done
in the context of תפילה tefillah that we would make a ברכת
המצוה Birkas HaMitzvah to introduce it is not so obvious.
What about, it might be the only example in which you say
a prayer in order to say a prayer?
Right, I
mean, again, right, absolutely.
Even ספירת העומר Sefiras HaOmer you make a...
well no, you do say like you say ה׳ שפתי תפתח, Hashem
sefasai tiftach, I mean you in a way you do a prayer
before the prayer שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. But the ברכת המצוה Birkas
HaMitzvah to introduce a prayer, right, heck, why don't we make a
ברכת המצוה Birkas HaMitzvah before ברכת המזון? Birkas HaMazon? ברוך אתה ה׳
אלהינו מלך העולם אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו לברך על המזון Baruch atah
Hashem Elokeinu Melech ha-olam asher kideshanu b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu l'vareich al hamazon and
then you do ברכת המזון, Birkas HaMazon, right? So the point is
once itself is a prayer we don't often make
a ברכת המצוה Birkas HaMitzvah before. Well so, that was with our
מנהג minhag to
end.
Without our מנהג minhag to end it's just a ברכה bracha and
then a מצוה. mitzvah. But with our מנהג minhag to end the
whole הלל becomes an extension, that's the way תוספות Tosafos understood it,
like a long type of a ברכה. bracha. But that's with our
מנהג minhag to end it. Let's start, we actually are somewhat caught
up. Let's start the next משנה. Mishna. אין מפטירין אחר הפסח אפיקומן.
Ein maftirin achar haPesach afikoman. The answer to the בן חכם. Ben
Chacham. Now
you do not depart or end after the פסח Pesach with an
אפיקומן. afikoman. So what is an אפיקומן? afikoman? It is not the
piece of מצה matzah as we'll see, the גמרא will discuss what
an אפיקומן afikoman is. But before we even get to that, I
want to indicate, it's אין מפטירין אחר הפסח. ein maftirin achar haPesach.
The assumption here that you're eating a קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, right,
is the assumption of the סיפא seifa of the פרק בזמן הבית
bizman habayis or שלא בזמן הבית? shelo bizman habayis? The first משנה
Mishna about the סדר not of the
פרק said ובמקדש היו מביאין לפניו גופו של פסח u-vamikdash hayu mevi'in
lefanav gufo shel pesach which indicated that we're not talking about... Then
you got to the questions of the four questions, which was הלילה
הזה כולו צלי *Halailah Hazeh Kulo Tzali*, which I indicated at the
time would either refer to זמן המקדש *Zman HaMikdash* or to the
מנהג *minhag* post-מקדש *Mikdash* that you would only eat roasted meat. This
משנה *Mishnah* that says אין מפטירין אחר הפסח אפיקומן *Ein Maftirin Achar
HaPesach Afikoman* seems to assume that, you know, you could say when
does the פסח *Pesach* you don't do it, but the fact that
it comes with no introduction seems to possibly suggest that it's taking
for granted that the context is זמן המקדש *Zman HaMikdash*.
Could
be, it's interesting, and as we will see from the next משניות
*Mishnayot*, the last few משניות *Mishnayot* all talk about eating the פסח
*Pesach* at night. So that is worth noting and I want to
underscore the point I made last time, which is: what did it
not talk about eating when we were talking about the סדר *Seder*?
What did it completely skip over? The eating of what? The משנה
*Mishnah* skipped over completely a discussion of the eating of the מצה
*matzah* and the מרור *marror*. What the heck was it doing skipping
it over? But if we're talking about זמן המקדש *Zman HaMikdash*, who
wants to talk about מצה *matzah* and מרור *marror*? What we should
be talking about is the eating of the פסח *Pesach*, right? That's
the only meal thing that matters; the מצה *matzah* and the מרור
*marror* are just accompaniments of it. So if we'll see, right, the
next משנה *Mishnah* לא יאכלו הפסח אחר חצות *Lo Yokhlu HaPesach Achar
Chatzot*, ישנו לא יאכלו הפסח אחר חצות *Yishnamu Lo Yokhlu HaPesach Achar
Chatzot*, ברכת הפסח *Birchat HaPesach*—the last few משניות *Mishnayot* all talk about
eating the פסח *Pesach*. So it's worth thinking about the idea that
these משניות *Mishnayot* minus the one that said בזמן המקדש *Bizman HaMikdash*
are assuming it's זמן המקדש *Zman HaMikdash* and therefore I'm not giving
a strong discussion to מצה *matzah* eating and am much more focused
now on the פסח *Pesach* eating.
Okay, isn't the רשב"ם *Rashbam* brings מצה *matzah* in right away?
I know, well we're going to get to it, well the גמרא
*Gemara*'s going to bring it in. Okay, so but anyway let's just
read one line in the גמרא *Gemara* about what this אפיקומן *Afikoman*
is that you can't have after the פסח *Pesach*. מאי אפיקומן *Mai
Afikoman*? What is this אפיקומן *Afikoman*? אמר רב *Amar Rav* שלא יעקור
מחבורה לחבורה *shelo ye'akor mechabura l'chabura*: don't leave one group and eat
in another one. Now, if there's a פסח *Pesach*, there's actually a
prohibition of eating the פסח *Pesach* in two חבורות *chaburot* as we
discussed before, so the רשב"ם *Rashbam* says it means don't even eat
other foods in another חבורה *chabura* because you'll come to eat the
פסח *Pesach* in another חבורה *chabura*. And that was a discussion earlier
in the גמרא *Gemara* about switching groups and so on.
You don't depart after the פסח *Pesach* with an אפיקומן *Afikoman* which
is going and eating in other groups. Now, how does the word
אפיקומן *Afikoman* mean eating in other groups? I won't tell you what
the רשב"ם *Rashbam* says which is trying to read it as a
Hebrew word. I will tell you that אפיקומן *Afikoman* is a Greek
word which actually means a type of a carousing that they did,
an after-party carousing. Okay, that after they would go out and have
their meal, then they'd go and visit other people and have their
meal and you know drink wine and carouse and spend some time
in one and then in another and it was obviously a lot
of licentious and inappropriate behavior. But that means, so again, thinking that
they styled aspects of the סדר *Seder* after the Greek meals with
the reclining and the wine, it's saying you know okay, but this
is a religious experience, so after the פסח *Pesach* don't go out
and carouse. Now the גמרא *Gemara* is reading it in less of
a moral way and more of a הלכה *halakhic* concern of, you
know, the קורבן פסח *Korban Pesach* can't be eaten in two places,
so don't go eat somewhere else, and the way the רשב"ם *Rashbam*
adds not just the פסח *Pesach*, but if you eat somewhere else
you'll come to eat the פסח *Pesach* itself in two places. Okay,
let's read one other explanation and we'll end there with now. שמואל
אמר *Shmuel amar* כגון אורדילאי לי וגוזליא לאבא *kegon urdilai li vegozlaya
l'abba*: it would mean even not in another place, even having a
dessert right here. What would be a dessert? So for me it
would be like various fungi, you know, mushrooms, and for אבא *Abba*,
which would be רב *Rav*, that would be like pigeons. So don't
have some dessert after the קורבן פסח *Korban Pesach*. רב חנינא בר
שילא ורבי יוחנן *Rav Chanina bar Shila v'Rabbi Yochanan* כגון תמרים קליות
ואגוזים *kegon temarim klayot v'egozim*: like dates and roasted wheat and nuts.
So don't eat, you know, תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן *Tanya kevatch d'Rabbi
Yochanan*: don't have dessert after the פסח *Pesach*. אין מפטירין אחר הפסח
כגון תמרים קליות ואגוזים *Ein maftirin achar ha-Pesach kegon temarim klayot v'egozim*.
Okay, don't have dessert afterwards and presumably there the reason is not
that you'll eat the פסח *Pesach* in the wrong place, but the
reason of keeping the taste of the פסח *Pesach* out of your
mouth—you want to keep the taste of the פסח *Pesach* in your
mouth. That's how we tend to interpret this, although the first explanation
is probably closer to the word אפיקומן *Afikoman* and we'll continue with
this discussion tomorrow.
שבת שלום *Shabbat Shalom*.